<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://kishanved.tech//feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://kishanved.tech//" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2024-07-21T14:04:37+00:00</updated><id>https://kishanved.tech//feed.xml</id><title type="html">Kishan Ved</title><subtitle>Kishan Ved&apos;s portfolio website. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">GSoC’24 Week 11</title><link href="https://kishanved.tech//blog/week11" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="GSoC’24 Week 11"/><published>2024-07-21T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-07-21T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://kishanved.tech//blog/week11</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://kishanved.tech//blog/week11"><![CDATA[<h5 id="july-15---july-21"><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">[July 15 - July 21]</code></h5> <h2 id="c-backend-for-treap-done">C++ backend for Treap done!</h2> <hr/> <h3 id="coding-info"><ins>Coding info</ins></h3> <p>This week, I finished coding up the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">C++ backend for Treap</code>. The following methods were implemented:</p> <ul> <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">Treap___new__()</code></li> <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">Treap___str__()</code></li> <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">Treap_search()</code></li> <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">Treap_insert()</code></li> <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">Treap_delete()</code></li> </ul> <h3 id="relevant-prs"><ins>Relevant PRs:</ins></h3> <p>PR for C++ backend for Treap (merged): <a href="https://github.com/codezonediitj/pydatastructs/pull/568">#568</a></p> <p>In the following week, I will add some additional functionality (like a few getter functions to access values and linking base class functions to derived classes) and this will complete the entire C++ backend for all trees present in <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">binary_trees.py</code> file.</p> <h3 id="learningsdifficulties"><ins>Learnings/Difficulties</ins></h3> <p>All going great!</p> <p><br/> Thanks to my mentor, <a href="https://github.com/czgdp1807">Gagandeep Singh</a>, for his support throughout.</p> <p>See you again after amazing 7 days! 😊</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Weekly_Blogs"/><category term="GSoC&apos;24"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[C++ backend for Treap done and merged!]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">GSoC’24 Week 10</title><link href="https://kishanved.tech//blog/week10" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="GSoC’24 Week 10"/><published>2024-07-14T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-07-14T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://kishanved.tech//blog/week10</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://kishanved.tech//blog/week10"><![CDATA[<h5 id="july-08---july-14"><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">[July 08 - July 14]</code></h5> <h2 id="first-gsoc-evaluation-passed-successfully">First GSoC Evaluation Passed Successfully!</h2> <hr/> <h3 id="coding-info"><ins>Coding info</ins></h3> <p>This week, I finished coding up the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">C++ backend for Cartesian Trees</code>. The following methods were implemented:</p> <ul> <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">CartesianTree___new__()</code></li> <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">CartesianTree___str__()</code></li> <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">CartesianTree_search()</code></li> <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">CartesianTree__bubble_up()</code></li> <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">CartesianTree__trickle_down()</code></li> <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">CartesianTree_insert()</code></li> <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">CartesianTree_delete()</code></li> <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">CartesianTree_root_idx()</code> : A getter function.</li> </ul> <p>Comprehensive tests were added and I ensured that all of them passed.</p> <h3 id="relevant-prs"><ins>Relevant PRs:</ins></h3> <p>PR for C++ backend for Cartesian Trees (merged): <a href="https://github.com/codezonediitj/pydatastructs/pull/567">#567</a></p> <p>In the following week, I will implement Treap in the C++ backend.</p> <h3 id="learningsdifficulties"><ins>Learnings/Difficulties</ins></h3> <p>This week, I learned about getter and setter functions and their implementation using the Python-C API. I created a getter function <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">CartesianTree_root_idx()</code> that accesses a member from a class much above in hierarchy (parent-&gt;parent-&gt;parent class).</p> <p><br/> Thanks to my mentor, <a href="https://github.com/czgdp1807">Gagandeep Singh</a>, for his support throughout.</p> <p>See you again after an awesome week! 😊</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Weekly_Blogs"/><category term="GSoC&apos;24"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[C++ backend for Cartesian Trees done for week 10 of GSoC!]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Image SuperResolution and Reconstruction</title><link href="https://kishanved.tech//blog/Image_SuperResolution_Reconstruction" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Image SuperResolution and Reconstruction"/><published>2024-07-14T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-07-14T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://kishanved.tech//blog/Image_SuperResolution_Reconstruction</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://kishanved.tech//blog/Image_SuperResolution_Reconstruction"><![CDATA[<h1 id="image-super-resolution-and-reconstruction">Image Super Resolution and Reconstruction</h1> <p>Important GitHub links to codes used to create this file:</p> <p>A) <a href="https://github.com/Kishan-Ved/Image-SuperResolution-Reconstruction/blob/main/Image_SuperResolution_Qualitative.ipynb">Qualitative Analysis</a> <span style="font-family: Times New Roman; font-size: 20px;"></span></p> <p>B) <a href="https://github.com/Kishan-Ved/Image-SuperResolution-Reconstruction/blob/main/Image_SuperResolution._Quantitative.ipynb">Quantitative Analysis</a> <span style="font-family: Times New Roman; font-size: 20px;"></span></p> <p>C) <a href="https://github.com/Kishan-Ved/Image-SuperResolution-Reconstruction/blob/main/Image_Reconstruction.ipynb">Image Reconstruction</a> <span style="font-family: Times New Roman; font-size: 20px;"></span></p> <h2 id="super-resolution-using-random-fourier-features-and-linear-regression">Super-Resolution Using Random Fourier Features and Linear Regression</h2> <h3 id="a-qualitative-analysis">$A.$ Qualitative Analysis</h3> <p>The provided code performs Qualitative Analysis of Super-Resolution on a given Image using a Linear Model trained on Random Fourier Features. Here is the breakdown of the code:</p> <ol> <li> <p><strong>Imports:</strong> The necessary libraries such as PyTorch, torchvision, matplotlib, urllib, numpy, sklearn, einops, and warnings are imported. All of these libraries are necessary for the code to run.</p> </li> <li> <p><strong>Loading the Image:</strong> The image of a dog as mentioned in the question is taken form the instructer’s code and read using <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">torchvision.io.read_image</code> function. The image is then displayed using matplotlib.</p> <div align="center"> <img src="./Ques4Img/ori_dog.png" alt="dog_img" width="80%"/> </div> <p>+</p> </li> <li> <p><strong>Scaling the RGB Values:</strong> The RGB values of the image are scaled from 0 to 1 using Min-Max scaler from the sklearn.preprocessing module. The formula for scaling the RGB values is given by:</p> <p><strong>[ X_{scaled} = \frac{X_{max}-X}{X_{max}-X_{min}} ]</strong><br/> where ( X_{max} ) and ( X_{min} ) are the maximum and minimum values of the RGB channels, respectively.</p> </li> <li> <p><strong>Cropping the Image:</strong> Due to the memory constraints, the size of the target image we took is 100 x 100. The image is cropped to this size using the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">torchvision.transforms.functional.crop</code> function.</p> <div align="center"> <img src="./Ques4Img/dog100.png" alt="dog_img" width="60%"/> </div> <p align="center">Cropped Image (100 x 100)</p> </li> <li> <p><strong>Creating Coordinate Map:</strong> A function is defined to create a coordinate map for the original image. The coordinate map consists of coordinates and corresponding to the pixel values of all the three channels (R G B).</p> </li> <li> <p><strong>Training the Linear Model:</strong> Another function is defined to train a linear model on the random Fourier features extracted from the coordinate map after scaling it. The model is trained using mean squared error loss and Adam optimizer.</p> </li> <li> <p><strong>Plotting Original vs. Enhanced Image:</strong> A function is defined to plot the original image and the enhanced image side by side.</p> </li> <li><strong>Enhancing the Image:</strong> An overall function that takes the original image, number of random Fourier features, sigma (kernel width for RBF sampler), learning rate, and number of epochs as input. It then creates random Fourier features, trains the linear model, and plots the original and enhanced images. <ul> <li> <p>The general equation for the Fourier basis functions can be expressed as follows:</p> <p><strong>For sine basis functions: [ \psi_k(x) = \sin(k \omega x + b_k) ]</strong></p> <p><strong>For cosine basis functions: [ \phi_k(x) = \cos(k \omega x + b_k) ]</strong></p> <p>Where:</p> <ul> <li>( k ) is the frequency index,</li> <li>( \omega ) is the angular frequency,</li> <li>( x ) is the input variable,</li> <li>( b_k ) is a randomly generated phase offset. (\newline)</li> </ul> </li> <li> <p>The bandwidth parameter <strong>( \sigma )</strong> influences the spread or width of the basis functions indirectly through the angular frequency <strong>( \omega )</strong>. Typically, <strong>( \omega = \frac{1}{\sigma} )</strong>. However, the direct inclusion of <strong>( \sigma )</strong> in the equation for Fourier basis functions is less common, as <strong>( \sigma )</strong> primarily affects the kernel function used in kernel methods rather than the basis functions themselves.</p> </li> </ul> </li> <li><strong>Enhancing the Image for Different Sigmas:</strong> The image is enhanced for different values of sigma for finding the better sigma (kernel width for RBF Sampler, it represents the bandwidth parameter of the fourier basis used for feature mapping), and the enhanced images are stored in a list. <ul> <li>For <strong>( \sigma )</strong> = 0.1</li> </ul> <div align="center"> <img src="./Ques4Img/dog_sigma01.png" alt="dog_img" width="50%"/> </div> <ul> <li>For <strong>( \sigma )</strong> = 0.04</li> </ul> <div align="center"> <img src="./Ques4Img/dog_sigma04.png" alt="dog_img" width="50%"/> </div> <ul> <li>For <strong>( \sigma )</strong> = 0.001</li> </ul> <div align="center"> <img src="./Ques4Img/dog_sigma001.png" alt="dog_img" width="50%"/> </div> <p>As you can see for higher <strong>( \sigma )</strong> values, the model is creating less complex decision boundaries and is not able to capture the fine details of the image. On the other hand, for lower <strong>( \sigma )</strong> values, the model is creating more complex decision boundaries and is able to capture the fine details of the image but further decreasing the <strong>( \sigma )</strong> value will lead to overfitting and the model will not be able to generalize well on the test data. This we can see in the image with <strong>( \sigma )</strong> = 0.001, the model has high variance.</p> </li> <li> <p><strong>Output:</strong> The comparison between the low-resolution image and the enhanced image is displayed for each sigma value. On comparison it is found that the image with the sigma value of around 0.04 gives the best results.</p> <ul> <li>For <strong>( \sigma )</strong> = 0.04</li> </ul> <div align="center"> <img src="./Ques4Img/dog_sigma04.png" alt="dog_img" width="50%"/> </div> </li> </ol> <p>The code effectively demonstrates Super-Resolution using a linear model trained on Random Fourier Features. It provides a qualitative comparison between the original and enhanced images, showing how the resolution is improved. Additionally, it allows experimenting with different values of sigma to observe their effects on the enhanced image over different bandwidths of the fourier basis used for feature mapping. We will also see the quantitative analysis in the next part of the question which will allow us to evaluate the performance of the super-resolution technique using RMSE and PSNR.</p> <p><strong>NOTE:</strong> <em>The quality of the output image depends on the choice of sigma (kernel width for RBF sampler) and the number of random Fourier features used, which can be further optimized using Hyperparameter Tuning.</em></p> <h3 id="b-quantitative-analysis">$B.$ Quantitative Analysis</h3> <p>The study can be further improved by adding quantitative analysis to evaluate the performance of the super-resolution technique. This can be done by calculating and comparing metrics such as Root Mean Square Error (RMSE) and Peak Signal-to-Noise Ratio (PSNR) between the Original $N$ x $N$ Image and Enhance $N$ x $N$ Image from $N/2$ x $N/2$ Image. Here is the breakdown of the code:</p> <ol> <li> <p><strong>Original Image (400 x 400):</strong><br/> The original image is the cropped image of size 400 x 400 pixels. This serves as the ground truth for comparison.</p> <div align="center"> <img src="./Ques4Img/dog_ground_truth.png" alt="dog_img" width="70%"/> </div> <p align="center">Ground Truth Image (400 x 400)</p> </li> <li> <p><strong>Low-Resolution Image (200 x 200):</strong><br/> The original image is downsampled using 2D convolution to create a low-resolution image with dimensions of 200 x 200 pixels.</p> <div align="center"> <img src="./Ques4Img/dog_lowres.png" alt="dog_img" width="70%"/> </div> <p align="center">Low-Resolution Image (200 x 200)</p> </li> <li> <p><strong>Generating Random Fourier Features:</strong><br/> Random Fourier features are generated for the scaled coordinates of the low-resolution image using the RBF Sampler. training a linear model on these features to learn the mapping from low to high resolution.</p> </li> <li> <p><strong>Training the Linear Model on RFF:</strong> The Linear Model has input features equal to the Random Fourier Features and the output features equal to the RGB values of the original image i.e, 3. The model is trained using mean squared error loss and Adam optimizer.</p> </li> <li><strong>Enhanced Image (400 x 400):</strong><br/> The learned model is then applied to the coordinate map of the low-resolution image to generate an enhanced version with dimensions of 400 x 400 pixels. <div align="center"> <img src="./Ques4Img/pred_dog.png" alt="dog_img" width="70%"/> </div> <p>[The image here formed is made with the sigma value of 0.03 and number of random Fourier features as 10000. As the 10000 features are not able to represent the data properly, the image is not enhanced properly and is not very comparable to the original image. This can be improved by increasing the number of random Fourier features which requires more computation and memory.]</p> </li> <li> <p><strong>Quantitative Metrics:</strong> The mean squared error (RMSE) and peak signal-to-noise ratio (PSNR) are calculated to quantitatively assess the similarity between the original and enhanced images. These metrics provide objective measures of the quality of the enhancement. The formulas for RMSE and PSNR are as follows:</p> <ul> <li> <p>Root Mean Square Error (RMSE): [ RMSE = \sqrt{\frac{1}{N} \sum_{i=1}^{N} (x_i - y_i)^2} ] where ( N ) is the total number of pixels in the image, ( x_i ) is the pixel value of the original image, and ( y_i ) is the pixel value of the enhanced image. We will calculate RMSE for each channel (R, G, B) and then take the sum of the three values.</p> </li> <li> <p>Peak Signal-to-Noise Ratio (PSNR): [ PSNR = 20 \log_{10}\left(\frac{MAX_I}{\sqrt{MSE}}\right) ] where ( MAX_I ) is the maximum possible pixel value (1.0 for scaled pixels values) and ( MSE ) is the mean squared error between the original and enhanced images.</p> </li> </ul> </li> <li><strong>Output:</strong> The RMSE and PSNR values that we got from the above calculations are as follows: <ul> <li>RMSE: 0.05166782811284065</li> <li>PSNR: 25.73858642578125</li> </ul> <p>The high PSNR value indicates that the enhanced image is very similar to the original image, and the low RMSE value further confirms this. The quantitative analysis provides a more objective evaluation of the super-resolution technique, allowing us to assess the effectiveness of the method in improving image resolution while preserving important features.</p> </li> </ol> <p>Overall, this approach allows for both qualitative and quantitative evaluation of the super-resolution technique. By comparing the original and enhanced images and calculating RMSE and PSNR, it provides insights into the effectiveness of the method in improving image resolution while preserving important features.</p> <h3 id="c-reconstruction-of-the-image">$C.$ Reconstruction of the Image</h3> <p>In this part, we randomly remove data from an image and then reconstruct it using random fourier features and linear regression.</p> <p>The following is the actual image:</p> <div align="center"> <img src="./Ques4Img/dog_ground_truth.png" alt="dog_img" width="70%"/> </div> <p>Now, we will randomly remove data from this image and reconstruct it. This image has a size of 400 x 400 pixels. For all the cases below, we use sigma 0.025 (for the RBF sampler) and 10000 random Fourier features.</p> <ol> <li> <p><strong>Remove 90% Data:</strong></p> <p>The image with 90% of the data removed is as follows:</p> <div align="center"> <img src="./Ques4Img/dog90.png" alt="dog_img" width="50%"/> </div> <p>The predicted image is:</p> <div align="center"> <img src="./Ques4Img/dog90p.png" alt="dog_img" width="90%"/> </div> <p>Root Mean Sqaured Error: 0.0786 PSNR: 22.08719840300042</p> </li> <li> <p><strong>Remove 80% Data:</strong></p> <p>The image with 80% of the data removed is as follows:</p> <div align="center"> <img src="./Ques4Img/dog80.png" alt="dog_img" width="50%"/> </div> <p>The predicted image is:</p> <div align="center"> <img src="./Ques4Img/dog80p.png" alt="dog_img" width="90%"/> </div> <p>Root Mean Sqaured Error: 0.0387 PSNR: 28.25418146450278</p> </li> <li> <p><strong>Remove 70% Data:</strong></p> <p>The image with 70% of the data removed is as follows:</p> <div align="center"> <img src="./Ques4Img/dog70.png" alt="dog_img" width="50%"/> </div> <p>The predicted image is:</p> <div align="center"> <img src="./Ques4Img/dog70p.png" alt="dog_img" width="90%"/> </div> <p>Root Mean Sqaured Error: 0.0330 PSNR: 29.63423604352773</p> </li> <li> <p><strong>Remove 60% Data:</strong></p> <p>The image with 60% of the data removed is as follows:</p> <div align="center"> <img src="./Ques4Img/dog60.png" alt="dog_img" width="50%"/> </div> <p>The predicted image is:</p> <div align="center"> <img src="./Ques4Img/dog60p.png" alt="dog_img" width="90%"/> </div> <p>Root Mean Sqaured Error: 0.0309 PSNR: 30.210612612395682</p> </li> <li> <p><strong>Remove 50% Data:</strong></p> <p>The image with 50% of the data removed is as follows:</p> <div align="center"> <img src="./Ques4Img/dog50.png" alt="dog_img" width="50%"/> </div> <p>The predicted image is:</p> <div align="center"> <img src="./Ques4Img/dog50p.png" alt="dog_img" width="90%"/> </div> <p>Root Mean Sqaured Error: 0.0301 PSNR: 30.43539642977963</p> </li> <li> <p><strong>Remove 40% Data:</strong></p> <p>The image with 40% of the data removed is as follows:</p> <div align="center"> <img src="./Ques4Img/dog40.png" alt="dog_img" width="50%"/> </div> <p>The predicted image is:</p> <div align="center"> <img src="./Ques4Img/dog40p.png" alt="dog_img" width="90%"/> </div> <p>Root Mean Sqaured Error: 0.0295 PSNR: 30.596299417410222</p> </li> <li> <p><strong>Remove 30% Data:</strong></p> <p>The image with 30% of the data removed is as follows:</p> <div align="center"> <img src="./Ques4Img/dog30.png" alt="dog_img" width="50%"/> </div> <p>The predicted image is:</p> <div align="center"> <img src="./Ques4Img/dog30p.png" alt="dog_img" width="90%"/> </div> <p>Root Mean Sqaured Error: 0.0292 PSNR: 30.686033211585062</p> </li> <li> <p><strong>Remove 20% Data:</strong></p> <p>The image with 20% of the data removed is as follows:</p> <div align="center"> <img src="./Ques4Img/dog20.png" alt="dog_img" width="50%"/> </div> <p>The predicted image is:</p> <div align="center"> <img src="./Ques4Img/dog20p.png" alt="dog_img" width="90%"/> </div> <p>Root Mean Sqaured Error: 0.0289 PSNR: 30.78619621879038</p> </li> <li> <p><strong>Remove 10% Data:</strong></p> <p>The image with 10% of the data removed is as follows:</p> <div align="center"> <img src="./Ques4Img/dog10.png" alt="dog_img" width="50%"/> </div> <p>The predicted image is:</p> <div align="center"> <img src="./Ques4Img/dog10p.png" alt="dog_img" width="90%"/> </div> <p>Root Mean Sqaured Error: 0.0286 PSNR: 30.86548449905607</p> </li> </ol> <h4 id="plots">Plots</h4> <h5 id="rmse-vs-percentage-of-data-removed">RMSE vs Percentage of Data Removed</h5> <p>The following plot shows the RMSE for different percentages of data removed from the image (denoted by x-axis):</p> <div align="center"> <img src="./Ques4Img/rmse.png" alt="dog_img" width="90%"/> </div> <h5 id="psnr-vs-percentage-of-data-removed">PSNR vs Percentage of Data Removed</h5> <p>The following plot shows the Peak Signal to Noise Ratio for different percentages of data removed from the image (denoted by x-axis):</p> <div align="center"> <img src="./Ques4Img/psnr.png" alt="dog_img" width="90%"/> </div> <h4 id="observations">Observations:</h4> <ol> <li>As we remove data, the rmse value increases as expected. This is because the error (with respect to the original image’s pixel values) increases, as we have less data to train the model.</li> <li>As we remove data, the peak SNR (signal to noise ratio) decreases. This is because now we have more data to train the model on, so the error (which is the noise) decreases.</li> </ol> <p>As we have lesser data to train on, our model cannot capture all the details of the image. We fit features based on data available and extrapolate these over unknown points, thus, we can’t capture all the details, rather, it’s an extrapolated approximation.</p> <p>10000 features have been used because of computational limitations. If the number of features are increased, then the model will be able to capture more details and the reconstructed image will be better.</p> <p>On increasing the value of sigma, the image becomes smoother and the details are not captured properly. On decreasing the value of sigma, the model overfits and the reconstructed image is not good. Thus, the value of sigma should be chosen carefully.</p> <p><strong>Changing sigma:</strong></p> <p>The image with 90% of the data removed is as follows:</p> <div align="center"> <img src="./Ques4Img/dog90.png" alt="dog_img" width="50%"/> </div> <p>The predicted image for sigma = 0.025 is:</p> <div align="center"> <img src="./Ques4Img/dog90p.png" alt="dog_img" width="90%"/> </div> <p>The predicted image for sigma = 0.03 is:</p> <div align="center"> <img src="./Ques4Img/dog90p2.png" alt="dog_img" width="90%"/> </div> <p>&lt;/span&gt;</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="ML"/><category term="ML"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A Machine Learning Project]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">GSoC’24 Week 9</title><link href="https://kishanved.tech//blog/week9" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="GSoC’24 Week 9"/><published>2024-07-07T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-07-07T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://kishanved.tech//blog/week9</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://kishanved.tech//blog/week9"><![CDATA[<h5 id="june-31---july-07"><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">[June 31 - July 07]</code></h5> <h2 id="first-evaluation-is-here">First Evaluation is here!</h2> <p>I’m officially at the middle of my Google Summer of Code 2024 program, but as I had started early, from the first week of May itself, I’ve completed a huge chunk of my GSoC project. The mid-term evaluation is coming up, which is from July 8 t July 12, and hence, here is all that I have achieved:</p> <h3 id="my-additions"><ins>My Additions:</ins></h3> <p>I have <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">3745 lines of code merged</code>, and I am the <a href="https://github.com/codezonediitj/pydatastructs/graphs/contributors?from=2019-06-16&amp;to=2024-07-08&amp;type=a"><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">#2 contributor by number of lines of code added</code></a>.</p> <ul> <li>Version changes: sphinx and myst_nb: <a href="https://github.com/codezonediitj/pydatastructs/pull/553"><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">PR #553</code></a></li> <li>C++ backend for Class Node: <a href="https://github.com/codezonediitj/pydatastructs/pull/556"><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">PR #556</code></a></li> <li>C++ backend for Class TreeNode: <a href="https://github.com/codezonediitj/pydatastructs/pull/556"><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">PR #556</code></a></li> <li>C++ backend for Class ArrayForTrees: <a href="https://github.com/codezonediitj/pydatastructs/pull/556"><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">PR #556</code></a></li> <li>C++ backend for Class Binary Trees: <a href="https://github.com/codezonediitj/pydatastructs/pull/556"><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">PR #556</code></a></li> <li>C++ backend for Class Binary Search Trees: <a href="https://github.com/codezonediitj/pydatastructs/pull/556"><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">PR #556</code></a></li> <li>C++ backend for Class Binary Tree Traversals: <a href="https://github.com/codezonediitj/pydatastructs/pull/556"><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">PR #556</code></a> <ul> <li>Depth First Search</li> <li>Pre-order traversal</li> <li>Post-order traversal</li> <li>In-order traversal</li> <li>Out-order traversal</li> <li>Breadth First Search</li> </ul> </li> <li>C++ backend for Class Self Balancing Binary Trees: <a href="https://github.com/codezonediitj/pydatastructs/pull/559"><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">PR #559</code></a></li> <li>C++ backend for Red Black Trees: <a href="https://github.com/codezonediitj/pydatastructs/pull/560"><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">PR #560</code></a></li> <li>C++ backend for Binary Indexed Trees: <a href="https://github.com/codezonediitj/pydatastructs/pull/561"><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">PR #561</code></a></li> <li>C++ backend for Splay Trees: <a href="https://github.com/codezonediitj/pydatastructs/pull/562"><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">PR #562</code></a></li> </ul> <h3 id="achievements"><ins>Achievements:</ins></h3> <p>The C++ backend provides <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">8-10 times faster code execution</code> than the Python backend. Here’s a benchmark test:</p> <div class="language-python highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="k">def</span> <span class="nf">test_BinarySearchTree</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="o">**</span><span class="n">kwargs</span><span class="p">):</span>
    <span class="n">cpp</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">Backend</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="n">CPP</span>
    <span class="n">repeat</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="mi">1</span>
    <span class="n">number</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="mi">1</span>

    <span class="n">size</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="nf">int</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">os</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="n">environ</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">get</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="sh">"</span><span class="s">PYDATASTRUCTS_BENCHMARK_SIZE</span><span class="sh">"</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="sh">"</span><span class="s">1000</span><span class="sh">"</span><span class="p">))</span>
    <span class="n">size</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">kwargs</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">get</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="sh">"</span><span class="s">size</span><span class="sh">"</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">size</span><span class="p">)</span>

    <span class="n">BST</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">BinarySearchTree</span>
    <span class="n">b1</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="nc">BST</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">backend</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="n">Backend</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="n">PYTHON</span><span class="p">)</span>
    <span class="n">b2</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="nc">BST</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">backend</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="n">Backend</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="n">CPP</span><span class="p">)</span>

    <span class="k">def</span> <span class="nf">f</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">backend</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">tree</span><span class="p">):</span>
        <span class="k">for</span> <span class="n">node</span> <span class="ow">in</span> <span class="nf">range</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="o">-</span><span class="mi">1000</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="mi">1000</span><span class="p">):</span>
            <span class="n">tree</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">insert</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">node</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">node</span><span class="p">)</span>
    <span class="k">def</span> <span class="nf">g</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">backend</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">tree</span><span class="p">):</span>
        <span class="k">for</span> <span class="n">node</span> <span class="ow">in</span> <span class="nf">range</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="o">-</span><span class="mi">1000</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="mi">1000</span><span class="p">):</span>
            <span class="n">tree</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">search</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">node</span><span class="p">)</span>
    <span class="k">def</span> <span class="nf">h</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">backend</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">tree</span><span class="p">):</span>
        <span class="k">for</span> <span class="n">node</span> <span class="ow">in</span> <span class="nf">range</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="mi">2000</span><span class="p">):</span>
            <span class="n">tree</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">delete</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">node</span><span class="p">)</span>

    <span class="n">kwds_dict_PY</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="p">{</span><span class="sh">"</span><span class="s">backend</span><span class="sh">"</span><span class="p">:</span> <span class="n">Backend</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="n">PYTHON</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="sh">"</span><span class="s">tree</span><span class="sh">"</span><span class="p">:</span><span class="n">b1</span><span class="p">}</span>
    <span class="n">kwds_dict_CPP</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="p">{</span><span class="sh">"</span><span class="s">backend</span><span class="sh">"</span><span class="p">:</span> <span class="n">Backend</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="n">CPP</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="sh">"</span><span class="s">tree</span><span class="sh">"</span><span class="p">:</span><span class="n">b2</span><span class="p">}</span>

    <span class="n">timer_python</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">timeit</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nc">Timer</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">functools</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">partial</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">f</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="o">**</span><span class="n">kwds_dict_PY</span><span class="p">))</span>
    <span class="n">python_insert</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="nf">min</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">timer_python</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">repeat</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">repeat</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">number</span><span class="p">))</span>

    <span class="n">timer_cpp</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">timeit</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nc">Timer</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">functools</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">partial</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">f</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="o">**</span><span class="n">kwds_dict_CPP</span><span class="p">))</span>
    <span class="n">cpp_insert</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="nf">min</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">timer_cpp</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">repeat</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">repeat</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">number</span><span class="p">))</span>
    <span class="k">assert</span> <span class="n">cpp_insert</span> <span class="o">&lt;</span> <span class="n">python_insert</span>

    <span class="n">timer_python</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">timeit</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nc">Timer</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">functools</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">partial</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">g</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="o">**</span><span class="n">kwds_dict_PY</span><span class="p">))</span>
    <span class="n">python_search</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="nf">min</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">timer_python</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">repeat</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">repeat</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">number</span><span class="p">))</span>

    <span class="n">timer_cpp</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">timeit</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nc">Timer</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">functools</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">partial</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">g</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="o">**</span><span class="n">kwds_dict_CPP</span><span class="p">))</span>
    <span class="n">cpp_search</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="nf">min</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">timer_cpp</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">repeat</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">repeat</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">number</span><span class="p">))</span>
    <span class="k">assert</span> <span class="n">cpp_search</span> <span class="o">&lt;</span> <span class="n">python_search</span>

    <span class="n">timer_python</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">timeit</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nc">Timer</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">functools</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">partial</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">h</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="o">**</span><span class="n">kwds_dict_PY</span><span class="p">))</span>
    <span class="n">python_delete</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="nf">min</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">timer_python</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">repeat</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">repeat</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">number</span><span class="p">))</span>

    <span class="n">timer_cpp</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">timeit</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nc">Timer</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">functools</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">partial</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">h</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="o">**</span><span class="n">kwds_dict_CPP</span><span class="p">))</span>
    <span class="n">cpp_delete</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="nf">min</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">timer_cpp</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">repeat</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">repeat</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">number</span><span class="p">))</span>
    <span class="k">assert</span> <span class="n">cpp_delete</span> <span class="o">&lt;</span> <span class="n">python_delete</span>

    <span class="nf">print</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="sh">"</span><span class="s">Python Time:</span><span class="sh">"</span><span class="p">)</span>
    <span class="nf">print</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="sh">"</span><span class="s">insert(): </span><span class="sh">"</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="n">python_insert</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="sh">"</span><span class="s">s</span><span class="sh">"</span><span class="p">)</span>
    <span class="nf">print</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="sh">"</span><span class="s">search(): </span><span class="sh">"</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="n">python_search</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="sh">"</span><span class="s">s</span><span class="sh">"</span><span class="p">)</span>
    <span class="nf">print</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="sh">"</span><span class="s">delete(): </span><span class="sh">"</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="n">python_delete</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="sh">"</span><span class="s">s</span><span class="sh">"</span><span class="p">)</span>
    <span class="n">python_total</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">python_insert</span><span class="o">+</span><span class="n">python_search</span><span class="o">+</span><span class="n">python_delete</span>
    <span class="nf">print</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="sh">"</span><span class="s">Total Python time: </span><span class="sh">"</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">python_total</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="sh">"</span><span class="s">s</span><span class="se">\n</span><span class="sh">"</span><span class="p">)</span>

    <span class="nf">print</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="sh">"</span><span class="s">C++ Time:</span><span class="sh">"</span><span class="p">)</span>
    <span class="nf">print</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="sh">"</span><span class="s">insert(): </span><span class="sh">"</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="n">cpp_insert</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="sh">"</span><span class="s">s</span><span class="sh">"</span><span class="p">)</span>
    <span class="nf">print</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="sh">"</span><span class="s">search(): </span><span class="sh">"</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="n">cpp_search</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="sh">"</span><span class="s">s</span><span class="sh">"</span><span class="p">)</span>
    <span class="nf">print</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="sh">"</span><span class="s">delete(): </span><span class="sh">"</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="n">cpp_delete</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="sh">"</span><span class="s">s</span><span class="sh">"</span><span class="p">)</span>
    <span class="n">cpp_total</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">cpp_insert</span><span class="o">+</span><span class="n">cpp_search</span><span class="o">+</span><span class="n">cpp_delete</span>
    <span class="nf">print</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="sh">"</span><span class="s">Total C++ time: </span><span class="sh">"</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">cpp_total</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="sh">"</span><span class="s">s</span><span class="se">\n</span><span class="sh">"</span><span class="p">)</span>

    <span class="nf">print</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="sh">"</span><span class="s">C++ backend is</span><span class="sh">"</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="nf">round</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">python_total</span><span class="o">/</span><span class="n">cpp_total</span><span class="p">),</span><span class="sh">"</span><span class="s">times faster!</span><span class="sh">"</span><span class="p">)</span>
    
<span class="nf">test_BinarySearchTree</span><span class="p">()</span>
</code></pre></div></div> <p>Output:</p> <div class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>Python Time:
insert():  7.025027044000126 s
search():  3.316694295000161 s
delete():  3.271200282000109 s
Total Python time:  13.612921621000396 s

C++ Time:
insert():  0.9178718929999832 s
search():  0.43746472500015443 s
delete():  0.7311443830001281 s
Total C++ time:  2.0864810010002657 s

C++ backend is 7 times faster!
</code></pre></div></div> <hr/> <h3 id="coding-info"><ins>Coding info</ins></h3> <p>This week, I finished coding up the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">C++ backend for AVL Trees</code>. The following methods were implemented:</p> <ul> <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">AVLTree__balance_delete()</code></li> <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">AVLTree_delete()</code></li> <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">AVLTree_rank()</code></li> <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">AVLTree_select()</code></li> </ul> <p>I have created a lightweight testing feature that runs all the test files excluding benchmark tests. This is useful to test locally, when the benchmark tests become too computationally heavy for the contributor’s machine to handle. I also modified one GitHub action to run only benchmark tests, saving both time and memory.</p> <h3 id="relevant-prs"><ins>Relevant PRs:</ins></h3> <p>PR for C++ backend for AVL Trees: <a href="https://github.com/codezonediitj/pydatastructs/pull/564">#564</a></p> <p>In the following week, I will implement the C++ backend for Cartesian Trees.</p> <h3 id="learningsdifficulties"><ins>Learnings/Difficulties</ins></h3> <p>No major difficulties this week, just a few random segmentation faults, which were not critical and were solved easily. Everything going smoothly, I’m enjoying my Google Summer of Code project!</p> <p><br/> Thanks to my mentor, <a href="https://github.com/czgdp1807">Gagandeep Singh</a>, for his support throughout.</p> <p>See you again after a productive week! 😊</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Weekly_Blogs"/><category term="GSoC&apos;24"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[C++ backend for AVL Trees and lightweighted testing feature.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">GSoC’24 Week 8</title><link href="https://kishanved.tech//blog/week8" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="GSoC’24 Week 8"/><published>2024-06-30T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-06-30T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://kishanved.tech//blog/week8</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://kishanved.tech//blog/week8"><![CDATA[<h5 id="june-24---june-30"><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">[June 24 - June 30]</code></h5> <h2 id="im-coding-ding-ding-ding">I’m Co..ding ding ding ding!</h2> <p>Incase you are wondering what the heading means, I’m emphasising the joy I get by coding all day. Its been 2 months since I started my <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">Google Summer of Code</code> project, and it has been an amazing and a rewarding journey. Cheers to another productive month of GSoC 2024.</p> <hr/> <h3 id="coding-info"><ins>Coding info</ins></h3> <p>This week, I finished coding up the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">C++ backend for Splay Trees</code>. The following methods were implemented:</p> <ul> <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">SplayTree_split()</code></li> <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">SplayTree_join()</code></li> <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">SplayTree_preorder()</code></li> <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">SplayTree_search()</code></li> </ul> <p>Comprehensive tests were added and I ensured that all of them passed.</p> <p>Next, I started working on implementing a <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">C++ backend for AVL Trees</code>. In this week, I implemented the following functions:</p> <ul> <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">AVLTree_left_height()</code></li> <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">AVLTree_right_height()</code></li> <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">AVLTree_balance_factor()</code></li> <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">AVLTree__right_rotate()</code></li> <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">AVLTree__left_right_rotate()</code></li> <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">AVLTree__right_left_rotate()</code></li> <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">AVLTree__left_rotate()</code></li> <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">AVLTree__balance_insertion()</code></li> <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">AVLTree_insert()</code></li> </ul> <h3 id="relevant-prs"><ins>Relevant PRs:</ins></h3> <p>PR for C++ backend for Splay Trees (merged): <a href="https://github.com/codezonediitj/pydatastructs/pull/562">#562</a></p> <p>PR for C++ backend for AVL Trees (work in progress): <a href="https://github.com/codezonediitj/pydatastructs/pull/564">#564</a></p> <p>In the following week, I will continue adding more functionality to the C++ backend of AVL Trees.</p> <h3 id="learningsdifficulties"><ins>Learnings/Difficulties</ins></h3> <p>Just one line: Patience and determination lead to resolution of bugs and segfaults.</p> <p><br/> Thanks to my mentor, <a href="https://github.com/czgdp1807">Gagandeep Singh</a>, for his support throughout.</p> <p>See you again after an amazing week! 😊</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Weekly_Blogs"/><category term="GSoC&apos;24"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[C++ backend for Splay Trees done! Started working on implementing a C++ backend for AVL Trees.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">GSoC’24 Week 7</title><link href="https://kishanved.tech//blog/week7" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="GSoC’24 Week 7"/><published>2024-06-23T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-06-23T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://kishanved.tech//blog/week7</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://kishanved.tech//blog/week7"><![CDATA[<h5 id="june-17---june-23"><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">[June 17 - June 23]</code></h5> <h2 id="eat--sleep--code--repeat">Eat + Sleep + Code + Repeat!</h2> <hr/> <h3 id="coding-info"><ins>Coding info</ins></h3> <p>This week, I coded up the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">C++ backend for Splay Trees</code>. The following methods were implemented:</p> <ul> <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">SplayTree__zig()</code></li> <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">SplayTree__zig_zig()</code></li> <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">SplayTree__zig_zag()</code></li> <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">SplayTree__zag_zag()</code></li> <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">SplayTree__zag_zig()</code></li> <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">SplayTree_splay()</code></li> <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">SplayTree_insert()</code></li> <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">SplayTree_delete()</code></li> </ul> <p>In case you find the names funny, just check out the code! They are all different functions with different roles, which are important for different insertions/deletions/algorithms in splay trees. (But I agree that the names sound funny 😀)</p> <h3 id="relevant-prs"><ins>Relevant PRs:</ins></h3> <p>PR for C++ backend for Splay Trees (work in progress): <a href="https://github.com/codezonediitj/pydatastructs/pull/562">#562</a></p> <p>In the following week, I will finish implementing Splay Trees in the C++ backend. Then, I will start making the C++ backend for the next tree data structure.</p> <h3 id="learningsdifficulties"><ins>Learnings/Difficulties</ins></h3> <p>I encountered some segmentation faults, and I used print statements to figure out the exact line where they occured. Used a little DSA here, did a binary search on the code to find the error :) .</p> <p><br/> Thanks to my mentor, <a href="https://github.com/czgdp1807">Gagandeep Singh</a>, for his support throughout.</p> <p>See you again after a productive week! 😊</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Weekly_Blogs"/><category term="GSoC&apos;24"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Worked on C++ backend for Splay Trees for week 7 of my Google Summer of Code.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">GSoC’24 Week 6</title><link href="https://kishanved.tech//blog/week6" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="GSoC’24 Week 6"/><published>2024-06-16T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-06-16T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://kishanved.tech//blog/week6</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://kishanved.tech//blog/week6"><![CDATA[<h5 id="june-10---june-16"><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">[June 10 - June 16]</code></h5> <h2 id="my-fingers-code-faster-than-i-can-think">My fingers code faster than I can think!</h2> <hr/> <h3 id="coding-info"><ins>Coding info</ins></h3> <p>In the first half of this week, I completed the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">Red Black Trees</code> class. In the second half, I worked on <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">Binary Indexed Trees</code> (which can also be interpreted as <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">Fenwick Trees</code>).</p> <p>For Red Black Trees, the following methods have been implemented in the C++ backend, and tested exhaustively:</p> <ul> <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">insert()</code> <ul> <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">_get_parent()</code></li> <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">_get_grand_parent()</code></li> <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">_get_sibling()</code></li> <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">_get_uncle()</code></li> <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">_is_onleft()</code></li> <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">_is_onright()</code></li> <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">__fix_insert()</code></li> </ul> </li> <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">delete()</code> <ul> <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">_find_predecessor()</code></li> <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">_transplant_values()</code></li> <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">_has_one_child()</code></li> <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">_is_leaf()</code></li> <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">_has_two_child()</code></li> <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">__has_red_child()</code></li> <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">_replace_node()</code></li> <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">__walk1_walk_isblack()</code></li> <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">__left_left_siblingcase()</code></li> <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">__right_left_siblingcase()</code></li> <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">__left_right_siblingcase()</code></li> <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">__right_right_siblingcase()</code></li> <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">__fix_deletion()</code></li> <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">_remove_node()</code></li> <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">_delete_root()</code></li> <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">__leaf_case()</code></li> <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">__one_child_case()</code></li> <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">__two_child_case()</code></li> </ul> </li> <li>All tree traversals (<strong>OOPS concepts used to resuse code</strong>)</li> </ul> <p>For Binary Indexed Trees, I’ve implemented the following methods in the C++ backend:</p> <ul> <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">update()</code></li> <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">get_prefix_sum()</code></li> <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">get_sum()</code></li> </ul> <h3 id="relevant-prs"><ins>Relevant PRs:</ins></h3> <p>PR for RedBlackTrees (merged): <a href="https://github.com/codezonediitj/pydatastructs/pull/560">#560</a></p> <p>PR for BinaryIndexedTrees (merged): <a href="https://github.com/codezonediitj/pydatastructs/pull/561">#561</a></p> <p>In the following week, I will implement Splay Trees in the C++ backend.</p> <h3 id="learningsdifficulties"><ins>Learnings/Difficulties</ins></h3> <p>Everything is now going smoothly! My fingers code faster than I can think! I’ve understood the process and now become good at it, yay.</p> <p><br/> Thanks to my mentor, <a href="https://github.com/czgdp1807">Gagandeep Singh</a>, for his support throughout.</p> <p>See you again after an amazing week! 😊</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Weekly_Blogs"/><category term="GSoC&apos;24"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Red Black Trees and Binary Indexed Trees completed!]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">GSoC’24 Week 5</title><link href="https://kishanved.tech//blog/week5" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="GSoC’24 Week 5"/><published>2024-06-09T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-06-09T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://kishanved.tech//blog/week5</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://kishanved.tech//blog/week5"><![CDATA[<h5 id="june-03---june-09"><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">[June 03 - June 09]</code></h5> <h2 id="pycon24-proposal-submitted-and-self-balancing-binary-trees-done">PyCon’24 proposal submitted and Self Balancing Binary Trees done!</h2> <hr/> <h3 id="coding-info"><ins>Coding info</ins></h3> <p>This week, I started and completed the C++ backend for Self Balancing Binary Tree class. The methods are:</p> <ul> <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">left_rotate()</code></li> <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">right_rotate()</code></li> <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">left_right_rotate()</code></li> <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">right_left_rotate()</code></li> </ul> <p>Along with this, <strong>I submitted my proposal for a talk at PyCon’24</strong>. If accepted, I will be presenting my work done in PyDataStructs as a part of Google Summer of Code 2024 at PyCon 2024, Bengaluru. Sounds exciting!</p> <p>PyCon’24 Proposal: <a href="https://in.pycon.org/cfp/2024/proposals/unleashing-pythons-power-lightning-fast-speed-with-a-c-backend~erkXw/">Unleashing Python’s Power: Lightning-fast speed with a C++ Backend</a></p> <p>Slides for the talk: <a href="https://drive.google.com/file/d/1K2DjwfJOrBZaMIlv5abQHZR0jxxO2yBE/view">Link</a></p> <p>Moreover, I started working on <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">RedBlackTrees</code> class. I have finished all helper methods for insert() and the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">insert()</code> method, which passes all the test cases and works correctly for all different conditions.</p> <p>I have added support for all tree traversals to the RedBlackTree class. These include:</p> <ul> <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">pre_order</code></li> <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">in_order</code></li> <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">post_order</code></li> <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">out_order</code></li> <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">depth_first_search</code></li> <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">breadth_first_search</code></li> </ul> <p><strong>OOPS concepts used greatly helped here. I can reuse the base code written for tree traversals in any tree data structure.</strong></p> <h3 id="relevant-prs"><ins>Relevant PRs:</ins></h3> <p>PR for Self Balancing Binary Trees (which has been merged): <a href="https://github.com/codezonediitj/pydatastructs/pull/559">#559</a></p> <p>PR for RedBlackTrees (work in progress): <a href="https://github.com/codezonediitj/pydatastructs/pull/560">#560</a></p> <p>In the following week, I will continue working on the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">RedBlackTree</code> class and add more functionality to its C++ backend. It includes methods like <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">delete()</code> and various helper methods required to handle all cases of deleting from the RedBlackTree. Following this, I will start implementing the next tree data structure: Binary Indexed Trees and it’s algorithms.</p> <h3 id="learningsdifficulties"><ins>Learnings/Difficulties</ins></h3> <p>This week, I felt confident and coded really fast, but at the same time, I ensured that the quality of code was not compromized. I have now learned to identify possible bugs and segfaults at the time of writing code itself, this has greatly increased my efficiency. I have mastered OOPS concepts and they have helped me greatly. For example, I can reuse the base code written for tree traversals in any tree data structure!</p> <p>I also learned to make an amazing proposal for a talk at PyCon’24 and prepared an outline for a talk of 30 minutes, with slides, to present at the conference.</p> <p><br/> Thanks to my mentor, <a href="https://github.com/czgdp1807">Gagandeep Singh</a>, for wonderful guidance for GSoC and helping me design an amazing talk for PyCon’24.</p> <p>See you again after a productive week! 😊</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Weekly_Blogs"/><category term="GSoC&apos;24"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[PyCon'24 proposal submitted and Self Balancing Binary Trees done!]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">PyCon 2024 Proposal</title><link href="https://kishanved.tech//blog/PyCon_proposal" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="PyCon 2024 Proposal"/><published>2024-06-06T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-06-06T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://kishanved.tech//blog/PyCon_proposal</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://kishanved.tech//blog/PyCon_proposal"><![CDATA[<h1 id="unleashing-pythons-power-lightning-fast-speed-with-a-c-backend">Unleashing Python’s Power: Lightning-fast speed with a C++ Backend</h1> <hr/> <h3 id="abstract">Abstract</h3> <p>Python is an amazing programming language, because of it’s simplicity, productivity and versatile ecosystem. However, when it comes to performance-critical tasks and numerical computing, the trade-off between ease of use and execution becomes a challenge. The solution to this: add a C++ backend! This retains all of Python’s amazing functionality in the frontend and harnesses the lightning fast execution speed of C++. Experience the process of accelerating any Python code by adding a C++ backend.</p> <h3 id="description">Description</h3> <p>PyDataStructs is an open source Python package for various data structures and algorithms, including their parallel implementations. As a part of Google Summer of Code 2024, I worked on adding a C++ backend for different tree data structures and their algorithms in PyDataStructs. This has greatly enhanced the speed of execution, making it 5-8 times faster. I have done this by extending Python with C++ using the Python C API. This allows the user to work in the simple and easy to understand Python frontend, while all the execution takes place in the C++ backend. The talk showcases the power of extending Python with C++ and provides an easy to understand demonstration of the same.</p> <p><strong>Outline of the talk</strong></p> <ul> <li>Introduction (2 minutes) <ul> <li>Welcome and a brief introduction of the speaker.</li> <li>Overview of the talk’s agenda and what the attendees can expect to learn.</li> </ul> </li> <li>What is PyDataStructs? (2 minutes) <ul> <li>Explaining PyDataStructs as an open source Python package for data structures and algorithms.</li> </ul> </li> <li>My contributions to PyDataStructs (1 minute) <ul> <li>A brief introduction of my work in Google Summer of Code 2024.</li> </ul> </li> <li>Speed benchmarks (1 minute) <ul> <li>Presenting performance benchmarks comparing Python and Python with a C++ backend.</li> </ul> </li> <li>Explaining the process of adding a C++ backend (an easy to understand example code will be used to support the points that follow) <ul> <li>Explaining what the example code’s objective is and showing the Python code. (1 minute)</li> <li>Introduction to Python C API (1 minute)</li> <li>Explaining how custom types are created (1 minute)</li> <li>Explaining how methods are defined (1 minute)</li> <li>Explaining how members are defined (1 minute)</li> <li>Explaining how memory is allocated and deallocated for custom types (1 minute)</li> <li>Explaining pointer reference: counting, increasing and decreasing (1 minute)</li> <li>Introducing setuptools and demonstrating how to build the module (1 minute)</li> <li>Comparing the performance of the C++ backend against only Python code for this example. (1 minute)</li> </ul> </li> <li>Demonstrating the C++ backend in PyDataStructs (4 minutes) <ul> <li>Showcasing how this has been done for an entire Python package.</li> <li>Demonstrating how OOPS concepts can be used in this.</li> <li>Exhibiting how the user can change the backend to C++ (from regular Python)</li> </ul> </li> <li>Conclusion and Takeaways (2 minutes) <ul> <li>Summarizing the key points covered in the talk.</li> <li>Encouraging attendees to extend their Python codes/packages with C++ by using the Python C API.</li> </ul> </li> <li>Q&amp;A session (5 minutes) <ul> <li>Allowing attendees to ask questions related to Python C API and PyDataStructs.</li> <li>Engaging in discussions and providing clarifications as needed.</li> </ul> </li> <li>Closing Remarks (1 minute) <ul> <li>Extending gratitude to the audience for their participation.</li> <li>Sharing contact information and additional resources for further exploration.</li> </ul> </li> </ul> <p><strong>Expected Takeaways</strong> Attendees will walk away with a comprehensive understanding of Python C API’s capabilities, its role in enhancing Python’s performance, and the practical steps to extend their Python projects with C/C++. They will be inspired to leverage the strengths of adding a C++ backend for amazingly fast computations without sacrificing Python’s user-friendly features.</p> <h3 id="speaker-information">Speaker information</h3> <p>Kishan Ved is a third year student at the Indian Institute of Technology Gandhinagar, India. He is pursuing a B.Tech degree in Computer Science and Engineering.</p> <p>Kishan has contributed to Google Summer of Code 2024. He has developed open source software for NumFOCUS organization’s project: PyDataStructs.</p> <p>Being the Head Boy of his school, he has delivered a speech in a stadium, to an audience of 1000+ people, on the annual sports day. Here is a clip from the speech: <a href="https://drive.google.com/file/d/1RtK_JPUGxIGHPMCT-JAw43ca922g0unf/view?usp=sharing">https://drive.google.com/file/d/1RtK_JPUGxIGHPMCT-JAw43ca922g0unf/view?usp=sharing</a></p> <h3 id="pre-requisites">Pre-requisites</h3> <p>Basic knowledge of Python. A brief idea about C++ would be helpful (though not an absolute necessity).</p> <h3 id="content-urls">Content URLs</h3> <p>PyDataStructs: Website: <a href="https://pydatastructs.readthedocs.io/en/stable/">https://pydatastructs.readthedocs.io/en/stable/</a></p> <p>PyDataStructs: GitHub: <a href="https://github.com/codezonediitj/pydatastructs">https://github.com/codezonediitj/pydatastructs</a></p> <p>Slides: <a href="https://drive.google.com/file/d/1K2DjwfJOrBZaMIlv5abQHZR0jxxO2yBE/view?usp=sharing">https://drive.google.com/file/d/1K2DjwfJOrBZaMIlv5abQHZR0jxxO2yBE/view?usp=sharing</a></p> <p>An example code will be used for explanation, as mentioned in the outline of the talk.</p> <h3 id="speaker-links">Speaker links</h3> <p>GitHub: <a href="https://github.com/Kishan-Ved">https://github.com/Kishan-Ved</a></p> <p>Google Summer of Code Blogs: <a href="https://kishanved.tech/blog/">https://kishanved.tech/blog/</a></p> <p>Email: kishanved123456@gmail.com</p> <p>LinkedIn: <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/kishan-ved-506140259/">https://www.linkedin.com/in/kishan-ved-506140259/</a></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="GSoC&apos;24"/><category term="PyCon&apos;24"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[My proposal for PyCon 2024, Bengaluru. Related to my work done in PyDataStructs during GSoC 2024.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">GSoC’24 Week 4</title><link href="https://kishanved.tech//blog/week4" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="GSoC’24 Week 4"/><published>2024-06-02T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-06-02T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://kishanved.tech//blog/week4</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://kishanved.tech//blog/week4"><![CDATA[<h5 id="may-27---june-02"><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">[May 27 - June 02]</code></h5> <h2 id="all-binarysearchtree-methods-and-all-tree-traversals-done-amazing-speed-results">All BinarySearchTree methods and all tree traversals done! Amazing speed results!</h2> <hr/> <h3 id="coding-info"><ins>Coding info</ins></h3> <p>This week, I completed all the methods of BinarySearchTree class. All of them can now be accessed in the C++ backend. This gives BinarySearchTree’s C++ backend the complete functionality. The methods are:</p> <ul> <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">delete()</code></li> <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">_simple_path()</code></li> <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">lower_bound</code></li> <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">upper_bound</code></li> <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">lowest common ancestor algorithm 1</code></li> <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">lowest common ancestor algorithm 2</code></li> <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">rank()</code></li> <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">select()</code></li> <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">str()</code></li> </ul> <p>Along with this, I also added all traversals in the BinaryTreeTraversal class. These include:</p> <ul> <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">pre_order</code></li> <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">in_order</code></li> <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">post_order</code></li> <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">out_order</code></li> <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">depth_first_search</code></li> <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">breadth_first_search</code></li> </ul> <h3 id="i-am-speed"><ins>I am speed!!!</ins></h3> <p>Now that I have completed the BinarySearchTree class, I decided to test it’s speed against the existing Python implementation and the results were amazing!!! <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">My implementations in the C++ backend are 6-8 times faster than the Python backend</code>.</p> <p>Here’s a benchmark test:</p> <div class="language-python highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="k">def</span> <span class="nf">test_BinarySearchTree</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="o">**</span><span class="n">kwargs</span><span class="p">):</span>
    <span class="n">cpp</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">Backend</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="n">CPP</span>
    <span class="n">repeat</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="mi">1</span>
    <span class="n">number</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="mi">1</span>

    <span class="n">size</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="nf">int</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">os</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="n">environ</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">get</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="sh">"</span><span class="s">PYDATASTRUCTS_BENCHMARK_SIZE</span><span class="sh">"</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="sh">"</span><span class="s">1000</span><span class="sh">"</span><span class="p">))</span>
    <span class="n">size</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">kwargs</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">get</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="sh">"</span><span class="s">size</span><span class="sh">"</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">size</span><span class="p">)</span>

    <span class="n">BST</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">BinarySearchTree</span>
    <span class="n">b1</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="nc">BST</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">backend</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="n">Backend</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="n">PYTHON</span><span class="p">)</span>
    <span class="n">b2</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="nc">BST</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">backend</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="n">Backend</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="n">CPP</span><span class="p">)</span>

    <span class="k">def</span> <span class="nf">f</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">backend</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">tree</span><span class="p">):</span>
        <span class="k">for</span> <span class="n">node</span> <span class="ow">in</span> <span class="nf">range</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="o">-</span><span class="mi">1000</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="mi">1000</span><span class="p">):</span>
            <span class="n">tree</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">insert</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">node</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">node</span><span class="p">)</span>
    <span class="k">def</span> <span class="nf">g</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">backend</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">tree</span><span class="p">):</span>
        <span class="k">for</span> <span class="n">node</span> <span class="ow">in</span> <span class="nf">range</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="o">-</span><span class="mi">1000</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="mi">1000</span><span class="p">):</span>
            <span class="n">tree</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">search</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">node</span><span class="p">)</span>
    <span class="k">def</span> <span class="nf">h</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">backend</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">tree</span><span class="p">):</span>
        <span class="k">for</span> <span class="n">node</span> <span class="ow">in</span> <span class="nf">range</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="mi">2000</span><span class="p">):</span>
            <span class="n">tree</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">delete</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">node</span><span class="p">)</span>

    <span class="n">kwds_dict_PY</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="p">{</span><span class="sh">"</span><span class="s">backend</span><span class="sh">"</span><span class="p">:</span> <span class="n">Backend</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="n">PYTHON</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="sh">"</span><span class="s">tree</span><span class="sh">"</span><span class="p">:</span><span class="n">b1</span><span class="p">}</span>
    <span class="n">kwds_dict_CPP</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="p">{</span><span class="sh">"</span><span class="s">backend</span><span class="sh">"</span><span class="p">:</span> <span class="n">Backend</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="n">CPP</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="sh">"</span><span class="s">tree</span><span class="sh">"</span><span class="p">:</span><span class="n">b2</span><span class="p">}</span>

    <span class="n">timer_python</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">timeit</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nc">Timer</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">functools</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">partial</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">f</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="o">**</span><span class="n">kwds_dict_PY</span><span class="p">))</span>
    <span class="n">python_insert</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="nf">min</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">timer_python</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">repeat</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">repeat</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">number</span><span class="p">))</span>

    <span class="n">timer_cpp</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">timeit</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nc">Timer</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">functools</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">partial</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">f</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="o">**</span><span class="n">kwds_dict_CPP</span><span class="p">))</span>
    <span class="n">cpp_insert</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="nf">min</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">timer_cpp</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">repeat</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">repeat</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">number</span><span class="p">))</span>
    <span class="k">assert</span> <span class="n">cpp_insert</span> <span class="o">&lt;</span> <span class="n">python_insert</span>

    <span class="n">timer_python</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">timeit</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nc">Timer</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">functools</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">partial</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">g</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="o">**</span><span class="n">kwds_dict_PY</span><span class="p">))</span>
    <span class="n">python_search</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="nf">min</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">timer_python</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">repeat</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">repeat</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">number</span><span class="p">))</span>

    <span class="n">timer_cpp</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">timeit</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nc">Timer</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">functools</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">partial</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">g</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="o">**</span><span class="n">kwds_dict_CPP</span><span class="p">))</span>
    <span class="n">cpp_search</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="nf">min</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">timer_cpp</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">repeat</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">repeat</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">number</span><span class="p">))</span>
    <span class="k">assert</span> <span class="n">cpp_search</span> <span class="o">&lt;</span> <span class="n">python_search</span>

    <span class="n">timer_python</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">timeit</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nc">Timer</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">functools</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">partial</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">h</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="o">**</span><span class="n">kwds_dict_PY</span><span class="p">))</span>
    <span class="n">python_delete</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="nf">min</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">timer_python</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">repeat</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">repeat</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">number</span><span class="p">))</span>

    <span class="n">timer_cpp</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">timeit</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nc">Timer</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">functools</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">partial</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">h</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="o">**</span><span class="n">kwds_dict_CPP</span><span class="p">))</span>
    <span class="n">cpp_delete</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="nf">min</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">timer_cpp</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">repeat</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">repeat</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">number</span><span class="p">))</span>
    <span class="k">assert</span> <span class="n">cpp_delete</span> <span class="o">&lt;</span> <span class="n">python_delete</span>

    <span class="nf">print</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="sh">"</span><span class="s">Python Time:</span><span class="sh">"</span><span class="p">)</span>
    <span class="nf">print</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="sh">"</span><span class="s">insert(): </span><span class="sh">"</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="n">python_insert</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="sh">"</span><span class="s">s</span><span class="sh">"</span><span class="p">)</span>
    <span class="nf">print</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="sh">"</span><span class="s">search(): </span><span class="sh">"</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="n">python_search</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="sh">"</span><span class="s">s</span><span class="sh">"</span><span class="p">)</span>
    <span class="nf">print</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="sh">"</span><span class="s">delete(): </span><span class="sh">"</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="n">python_delete</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="sh">"</span><span class="s">s</span><span class="sh">"</span><span class="p">)</span>
    <span class="n">python_total</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">python_insert</span><span class="o">+</span><span class="n">python_search</span><span class="o">+</span><span class="n">python_delete</span>
    <span class="nf">print</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="sh">"</span><span class="s">Total Python time: </span><span class="sh">"</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">python_total</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="sh">"</span><span class="s">s</span><span class="se">\n</span><span class="sh">"</span><span class="p">)</span>

    <span class="nf">print</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="sh">"</span><span class="s">C++ Time:</span><span class="sh">"</span><span class="p">)</span>
    <span class="nf">print</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="sh">"</span><span class="s">insert(): </span><span class="sh">"</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="n">cpp_insert</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="sh">"</span><span class="s">s</span><span class="sh">"</span><span class="p">)</span>
    <span class="nf">print</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="sh">"</span><span class="s">search(): </span><span class="sh">"</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="n">cpp_search</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="sh">"</span><span class="s">s</span><span class="sh">"</span><span class="p">)</span>
    <span class="nf">print</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="sh">"</span><span class="s">delete(): </span><span class="sh">"</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="n">cpp_delete</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="sh">"</span><span class="s">s</span><span class="sh">"</span><span class="p">)</span>
    <span class="n">cpp_total</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">cpp_insert</span><span class="o">+</span><span class="n">cpp_search</span><span class="o">+</span><span class="n">cpp_delete</span>
    <span class="nf">print</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="sh">"</span><span class="s">Total C++ time: </span><span class="sh">"</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">cpp_total</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="sh">"</span><span class="s">s</span><span class="se">\n</span><span class="sh">"</span><span class="p">)</span>

    <span class="nf">print</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="sh">"</span><span class="s">C++ backend is</span><span class="sh">"</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="nf">round</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">python_total</span><span class="o">/</span><span class="n">cpp_total</span><span class="p">),</span><span class="sh">"</span><span class="s">times faster!</span><span class="sh">"</span><span class="p">)</span>
    
<span class="nf">test_BinarySearchTree</span><span class="p">()</span>
</code></pre></div></div> <p>Output:</p> <div class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>Python Time:
insert():  7.025027044000126 s
search():  3.316694295000161 s
delete():  3.271200282000109 s
Total Python time:  13.612921621000396 s

C++ Time:
insert():  0.9178718929999832 s
search():  0.43746472500015443 s
delete():  0.7311443830001281 s
Total C++ time:  2.0864810010002657 s

C++ backend is 7 times faster!
</code></pre></div></div> <h3 id="relevant-prs"><ins>Relevant PRs:</ins></h3> <p>I worked on the PR: <a href="https://github.com/codezonediitj/pydatastructs/pull/556">#556</a></p> <p>There have been a plethora of commits to this PR. Commits of this week focused on adding all the methods and completing the BinarySearchTree class, adding all traversals and adding benchmark tests.</p> <p>In the following week, I will work on <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">SelfBalancingBinaryTree</code> class and add all its functionality in the C++ backend. It includes methods like <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">_right_rotate()</code>, <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">_left_rotate</code>, <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">_left_right_rotate</code> and <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">_right_left_rotate</code>. Hence, it serves as the base class for AVL Trees, Cartesian Trees, Splay Trees and Red Black Trees.</p> <h3 id="learningsdifficulties"><ins>Learnings/Difficulties</ins></h3> <p>This week was amazing, I was busy working and I achieved several goals! I faced some difficulty specific to the Python-C API, and I spent time referring to its documentation. After hours of reading the documentation, I finally figured out the solution! This taught me the importance to document work and read the documentation (something that most enthusiastic coders like me skip).</p> <p><br/> Thanks to my mentor, <a href="https://github.com/czgdp1807">Gagandeep Singh</a>, for guiding me whenever requested.</p> <p>See you again after amazing 7 days! 😊</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Weekly_Blogs"/><category term="GSoC&apos;24"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[All BinarySearchTree methods and all tree traversals done! Amazing speed results!]]></summary></entry></feed>